Before I get to bulk of what I have to say,
قبل أن أتطرّق إلى جملة ما سأقوله،
I feel compelled just to mention a couple of things about myself.
أجد نفسي مضطراً لذكر بضعة أشياء عن نفسي.
I am not some mystical,
لستُ من أولئك الأشخاص
spiritual sort of person.
الباطنيين والروحانيّين.
I'm a science writer.
أنا مؤلّف دراسات علميّة.
I studied physics in college.
درستُ الفيزياء في الكلّية.
I used to be a science correspondent for NPR.
كنتُ مراسل دراسات علميّة لدى NPR.
OK, that said:
حسناً، من هذا المنطلق:
in the course of working on a story for NPR,
ضمن مسار عملي على مقالة لـ NPR،
I got some advice from an astronomer
تلقّيتُ نصيحةً من عالم فلك
that challenged my outlook,
والتي تحدّت نظرتي،
and frankly, changed my life.
وبصراحة، غيّرتْ حياتي.
You see, the story was about an eclipse,
في الواقع، كانت المقالة عن كسوف الشمس،
a partial solar eclipse that was set to cross the country
كان كسوفاً شمسياً جزئياً شهِدَه البلد
in May of 1994.
في مايو من العام 1994.
And the astronomer -- I interviewed him,
وعندما أجريتُ مقابلةً مع العالم الفلكي،
and he explained what was going to happen and how to view it,
شرح ما الذي كان سيحدث وكيف سيتمّ رصد الواقعة،
but he emphasized that, as interesting as a partial solar eclipse is,
لكنّه أكّدَ على أنّه وبقدر ما الكسوف الشمسي الجزئي مثير للاهتمام،
a much rarer total solar eclipse is completely different.
فإنّ كسوفاً شمسياً كاملاً أكثر ندرة هو مسألة مختلفة تماماً.
In a total eclipse, for all of two or three minutes,
في الكسوف الشمسي الكامل، لمدّة دقيقتين أو ثلاث،
the moon completely blocks the face of the sun,
يحجب القمر وجهَ الشّمس تماماً،
creating what he described as the most awe-inspiring spectacle
ليخلق ما وصفَه بأنّه أكثر مشهد مهيب
in all of nature.
في الطبيعة برمّتها.
And so the advice he gave me was this:
وبالتالي كانت النصيحة التي أسداها لي:
"Before you die," he said,
قال: "قبل أن تموت،
"you owe it to yourself to experience a total solar eclipse."
أنت مدين لنفسك بتجربة كسوف شمسي كامل."
Well honestly, I felt a little uncomfortable
بصراحة، شعرتُ بارتباك بعض الشيء
hearing that from someone I didn't know very well;
لدى سماعي ذلك من شخص لم تربطني به معرفة عميقة،
it felt sort of intimate.
شعرتُ بشيء من الحميميّة.
But it got my attention, and so I did some research.
لكن لفت ذلك اهتمامي، وبالتالي أجريتُ بحثاً.
Now the thing about total eclipses is,
والآن فيما يتعلّق بالكسوف الشمسي الكامل،
if you wait for one to come to you,
إن انتظرت شخصاً كي يأتي إليك،
you're going to be waiting a long time.
فسوف تنتظر فترة طويلة.
Any given point on earth experiences a total eclipse
إنّ أي بقعة في الأرض تخضع لكسوفٍ كامل
about once every 400 years.
حوالي مرّة واحدة في كلّ 400 عام.
But if you're willing to travel, you don't have to wait that long.
لكن إن نويتَ السّفر، لست مضطراً للانتظار هذه المدّة الطويلة.
And so I learned that a few years later, in 1998,
وهكذا علمتُ أنّه بعد بضع سنوات، في 1998،
a total eclipse was going to cross the Caribbean.
ستشهد جزر الكاريبي كسوفاً كاملاً.
Now, a total eclipse is visible only along a narrow path,
والكسوف الكامل يكون مرئياً ضمن مسار ضيّق فقط،
about a hundred miles wide,
بعرض مئة ميل تقريباً،
and that's where the moon's shadow falls.
وفي هذا المسار يتشكّل ظلّ القمر.
It's called the "path of totality."
يُدعى بـ"مسار الكليّة."
And in February 1998,
وفي فبراير من العام 1998،
the path of totality was going to cross Aruba.
كان مسار الكلّية سيمرّ بأروبا.
So I talked to my husband, and we thought: February? Aruba?
لذا تكلّمتُ مع زوجي وتساءلنا: فبراير؟ أروبا؟
Sounded like a good idea anyway.
بدَتْ فكرة جيّدة على أي حال.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So we headed south,
لذا توجّهنا جنوباً،
to enjoy the sun and to see what would happen
للتمتُّع بمنظر الشمس ورؤية ما سيحدث
when the sun briefly went away.
عندما تختفي الشمس لفترةٍ قصيرة.
Well, the day of the eclipse found us and many other people
حسناً، أطلَّ علينا نهار الكسوف وكثير من الناس الآخرين
out behind the Hyatt Regency,
خلف هايت ريجنسي،
on the beach,
على الشاطئ،
waiting for the show to begin.
ننتظرون بدء العرض.
And we wore eclipse glasses with cardboard frames
وارتدينا نظّارات الكسوف ذات الإطارات الكرتونيّة
and really dark lenses that enabled us to look at the sun safely.
وعدسات داكنة جداً أتاحت لنا إمكانية رؤية الشمس بأمان.
A total eclipse begins as a partial eclipse,
يبدأ الكسوف الشمسي الكامل ككسوف جزئي،
as the moon very slowly makes its way in front of the sun.
بينما يشقّ القمرُ طريقَه على مهل من أمام الشمس.
So first it looked the sun had a little notch in its edge,
لذا بدت الشمس في البداية وكأن في طرفها أخدود صغير،
and then that notch grew larger and larger,
ومن ثمّ نما هذا الأخدود أكثر فأكثر،
turning the sun into a crescent.
ليحوّل الشمس إلى هلال.
And it was all very interesting, but I wouldn't say it was spectacular.
وكان ذلك مثيراً جداً للاهتمام، لكن لا أقول أنّه مذهل.
I mean, the day remained bright.
أعني أنّ النهار ظلّ مشرقاً.
If I hadn't known what was going on overhead,
لو لم أكن قد علمتُ بما كان يجري فوق رأسي،
I wouldn't have noticed anything unusual.
لما لاحظتُ أي شيء غير مألوف.
Well, about 10 minutes before the total solar eclipse was set to begin,
حسناً، قبل حوالي 10 دقائق من الكسوف الشمسي الكامل الذي كان مقرراً أن يبدأ،
weird things started to happen.
بدأت أمور غريبة بالحدوث.
A cool wind kicked up.
بدأت تهبّ رياح باردة.
Daylight looked odd, and shadows became very strange;
بدا ضوء النهار غريباً، وغدت الظلال عجيبة،
they looked bizarrely sharp,
بدَتْ حادّة على نحو غريب،
as if someone had turned up the contrast knob on the TV.
وكأنّ شخصاً قد رفع من مستوى التباين في التلفزيون.
Then I looked offshore, and I noticed running lights on boats,
ثمّ نظرتُ بعيداً على الشاطئ فلاحظتُ أضواء القوارب،
so clearly it was getting dark,
لذا كان من الواضح أنّ الظلام يخيّم،
although I hadn't realized it.
رغم أنني لم أكن قد أدركت ذلك.
Well soon, it was obvious it was getting dark.
بعد فترة قصيرة، كان واضحاً أنّ الظلام قد خيّم.
It felt like my eyesight was failing.
شعرتُ وكأن بصري ينحسر.
And then all of a sudden,
ومن ثمّ وبشكل مفاجئ،
the lights went out.
تلاشت الأضواء.
Well, at that,
وعند ذلك،
a cheer erupted from the beach,
تعالت هتافات من الشاطئ،
and I took off my eclipse glasses,
وخلعتُ نظّارة الكسوف خاصّتي،
because at this point during the total eclipse,
لأنّ في هذه المرحلة من الكسوف الكلّي،
it was safe to look at the sun with the naked eye.
كان النظر إلى الشمس بعين مجرّدة آمناً.
And I glanced upward,
وألقيتُ نظرة سريعة للأعلى،
and I was just dumbstruck.
وكنتُ مذهولاً تماماً.
Now, consider that, at this point, I was in my mid-30s.
خذ بعين الاعتبار أنني كنتُ في هذه المرحلة في منتصف الثلاثينات.
I had lived on earth long enough to know what the sky looks like.
لقد عشتُ في الأرض فترة كافية لمعرفة شكل السماء.
I mean --
أعني...
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I'd seen blue skies and grey skies
لقد رأيتُ سماء زرقاء وسماء رمادية
and starry skies and angry skies
وسماء مرصّعة بالنجوم وسماء مضطربة
and pink skies at sunrise.
وسماء ورديّة عند شروق الشمس.
But here was a sky I had never seen.
بينما هنا رأيتُ سماء لم أرها من قبل.
First, there were the colors.
أولاً، كان هنالك الألوان.
Up above, it was a deep purple-grey,
كان اللون من فوقي رمادياً أرجوانياً غامقاً.
like twilight.
كالشفق.
But on the horizon it was orange,
لكن كان اللون برتقالياً في الأفق،
like sunset,
كغروب الشمس،
360 degrees.
360 درجة.
And up above, in the twilight,
ومن فوقي، في الشفق،
bright stars and planets had come out.
ظهرت كواكب ونجوم ساطعة.
So there was Jupiter
أي كوكب المشتري
and there was Mercury
وكوكب عُطارد
and there was Venus.
وكوكب الزهرة.
They were all in a line.
ظهروا جميعاً على شكل خط.
And there, along this line,
وعلى امتداد هذا الخط،
was this thing,
ظهر هذا الشيء،
this glorious, bewildering thing.
هذا الشيء المذهل البهيّ.
It looked like a wreath woven from silvery thread,
بدا وكأنّه إكليل منسوج من خيط فضّي،
and it just hung out there in space, shimmering.
فتدلّى في الفضاء يسطع بريقاً.
That was the sun's outer atmosphere,
كان ذلك الشيء هو الغلاف الجوي الخارجي للشمس،
the solar corona.
هالة الشمس.
And pictures just don't do it justice.
والصور لا تكفي للتعبير عن ذلك.
It's not just a ring or halo around the sun;
إنها ليست مجرد حلقة أو هالة محيطة بالشمس،
it's finely textured, like it's made out of strands of silk.
إنّها مزخرفة بجودة عالية، كما لو صُنعت من خيوط حريريّة.
And although it looked nothing like our sun,
ورغم أنها لم تشبه شمسنا على الإطلاق،
of course, I knew that's what it was.
إلّا أنني عرفتُ ما هي بالطبع.
So there was the sun, and there were the planets,
لذا كانت هناك الشمس، وكانت هناك الكواكب،
and I could see how the planets revolve around the sun.
واستطعت رؤية دوران الكواكب حول الشمس.
It's like I had left our solar system
شعرتُ وكأنني غادرتُ نظامنا الشمسي
and was standing on some alien world,
ووقفتُ في عالم غريب ما،
looking back at creation.
أتأمّل الخلق.
And for the first time in my life,
وللمرّة الأولى في حياتي،
I just felt viscerally connected to the universe
شعرتُ نفسي متّصلاً بالكون على نحوٍ عميق
in all of its immensity.
بكلِّ ضخامته.
Time stopped,
توقّف الزمن،
or it just kind of felt nonexistent,
أو انتابني شعور بالانعداميّة فحسب،
and what I beheld with my eyes --
وما شهدته عيناي...
I didn't just see it,
لم أره فقط،
it felt like a vision.
بل بدا وكأنه رؤيا.
And I stood there in this nirvana
ووقفتُ هناك وسط هذه السعادة المُطلقة
for all of 174 seconds -- less than three minutes --
لمدّة 174 ثانية... أقل من ثلاث دقائق...
when all of a sudden, it was over.
عندما انتهى كلّ شيء فجأة.
The sun burst out,
انبثقت الشمس،
the blue sky returned,
وعادت السماء الزرقاء،
the stars and the planets and the corona were gone.
وقد اختفت النجوم والكواكب والهالة.
The world returned to normal.
وعاد العالم إلى طبيعته.
But I had changed.
لكنني قد تغيّرت.
And that's how I became an umbraphile --
وهكذا أصبحتُ راصداً...
an eclipse chaser.
ومُطارداً للكسوف.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So, this is how I spend my time and hard-earned money.
وهكذا استهلكتُ وقتي وأنفقتُ مالي المُكتسَب بعرق جبيني.
Every couple of years, I head off to wherever the moon's shadow will fall
في كل بضع سنوات، أتوجّه إلى حيث سيسقط ظلّ القمر
to experience another couple minutes
لأعيش هذا الهناء الكوني
of cosmic bliss,
لبضع دقائق أخرى،
and to share the experience with others:
ولمشاركة التجربة مع الآخرين:
with friends in Australia,
مع أصدقاء في أستراليا،
with an entire city in Germany.
مع مدينة كاملة في ألمانيا.
In 1999, in Munich, I joined hundreds of thousands
في 1999 في ميونيخ، انضممتُ لمئات الآلاف
who filled the streets and the rooftops and cheered in unison
الذين ملؤوا الشوارع والسطوح وهتفوا معاً في آن واحد
as the solar corona emerged.
مع ظهور الهالة الشمسيّة.
And over time, I've become something else:
ومع الوقت، تحوّلتُ لشيء آخر:
an eclipse evangelist.
مُبشّرًا بالكسوف.
I see it as my job
أعتبر هذا عملي.
to pay forward the advice that I received all those years ago.
لأدفع بالنصيحة التي تلقّيتُها طوال تلك السنوات التي مضت لغيري.
And so let me tell you:
لذا دعوني أخبركم بالتالي:
before you die,
قبل أن تموتوا:
you owe it to yourself to experience a total solar eclipse.
أنتم مدينون لأنفسكم بتجربة كسوف شمسي كامل.
It is the ultimate experience of awe.
إنها تجربة الذهول المثاليّة.
Now, that word, "awesome," has grown so overused
إن كلمة "رائع" قد استُخدِمت بإفراط
that it's lost its original meaning.
لدرجة أنها فقدت معناها الأصلي.
True awe, a sense of wonder and insignificance
الذهول الحقيقي، الشعور بالدهشة والتفاهة
in the face of something enormous and grand,
أمام شيء عملاق وهائل،
is rare in our lives.
هو أمر نادر في حياتنا.
But when you experience it, it's powerful.
لكن عندما تخضع لهذه التجربة، تشعر بوقع قوّتها.
Awe dissolves the ego.
الذهول يُذيب الأنا.
It makes us feel connected.
يجعلنا نشعر بالاتّصال.
Indeed, it promotes empathy and generosity.
صدقاً، يعزّز الشعور بالتعاطف والتسامح.
Well, there is nothing truly more awesome than a total solar eclipse.
حسناً، لا شيء أكثر روعة من كسوف شمسي كامل.
Unfortunately, few Americans have seen one,
مع الأسف، عدد قليل من الأمريكيّين قد رأوا كسوفاً،
because it's been 38 years
لأنّه مضى 38 عاماً
since one last touched the continental United States
منذ حدوث الكسوف آخر مرّة في الولايات الأمريكية المتجاورة
and 99 years since one last crossed the breadth of the nation.
و99 عاماً منذ حدوث الكسوف آخر مرّة ضمن نطاق الدولة.
But that is about to change.
لكن ذلك على وشك أن يتغيّر.
Over the next 35 years,
على مدى الـ35 عاماً القادم،
five total solar eclipses will visit the continental United States,
ستشهد الولايات الأمريكية المتجاورة خمس ظواهر كسوف شمسية كاملة،
and three of them will be especially grand.
وستكون ثلاثة منها تحديداً هائلة.
Six weeks from now, on August 21, 2017 --
بعد ستّة أسابيع من الآن، في 21 أغسطس من العام 2017...
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
the moon's shadow will race from Oregon to South Carolina.
سينطلق ظلّ القمر مسرعاً من أوريغون إلى كارولاينا الجنوبية.
April 8, 2024, the moon's shadow heads north from Texas to Maine.
وفي 8 أبريل من 2024، سيتوجّه القمر شمالاً من تكساس إلى مين.
In 2045, on August 12,
في 2045، في 12 أغسطس،
the path cuts from California to Florida.
يمرّ المسار من كاليفورنيا إلى فلوريدا.
I say:
أقول:
What if we made these holidays?
ماذا لو جعلنا هذه الأيّام عُطلاً؟
What if we --
ماذا لو...
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
What if we all stood together,
ماذا لو وقفنا جميعاً معاً،
as many people as possible,
بأكبر عدد ممكن من الناس،
in the shadow of the moon?
في ظلّ القمر؟
Just maybe, this shared experience of awe would help heal our divisions,
لعلّ تجربة الذهول المشتركة هذه ستساهم في شفائنا من انقساماتنا،
get us to treat each other just a bit more humanely.
وتمكّننا من معاملة بعضنا بإنسانيّة أكبر فحسب،
Now, admittedly, some folks consider my evangelizing a little out there;
في الحقيقة، يعتبر بعض الناس تبشيري مبالغاً به قليلاً،
my obsession, eccentric.
وهوسي غريب الأطوار.
I mean, why focus so much attention on something so brief?
أعني، لمَ تركيز كلّ هذا الانتباه على شيء قصير جدّاً؟
Why cross the globe -- or state lines, for that matter --
لمَ السفر إلى أرجاء الأرض أو تخطّي حدود البلاد لذلك الغرض...
for something that lasts three minutes?
لشيء يدوم ثلاث دقائق؟
As I said:
كما قلت:
I am not a spiritual person.
لستُ شخصاً روحانياً.
I don't believe in God.
لا أؤمن بالله.
I wish I did.
ليتني آمنت.
But when I think of my own mortality --
لكن كلّما فكّرتُ بأنني شخص فانٍ
and I do, a lot --
وأفعل ذلك كثيراً...
when I think of everyone I have lost,
كلّما فكّرتُ في كل من فقدت،
my mother in particular,
ولاسيّما أمّي،
what soothes me
ما يريحني
is that moment of awe I had in Aruba.
هو لحظة الذهول تلك التي عشتها في أروبا.
I picture myself on that beach,
أتخيّل نفسي على ذلك الشاطئ،
looking at that sky,
أتأمّل تلك السّماء،
and I remember how I felt.
وأتذكّر الشعور الذي انتابني.
My existence may be temporary,
لعلّ وجودي يكون مؤقتاً،
but that's OK because, my gosh,
لكن لا بأس في ذلك والسبب، يا إلهي،
look at what I'm a part of.
انظروا من أي شيء أصبحتُ جزءاً.
And so this is a lesson I've learned,
وبالتالي هذا درس قد تعلّمتُه،
and it's one that applies to life in general:
إنه الدرس الذي ينطبق على الحياة بشكل عام:
duration of experience does not equal impact.
مدّة التجربة لا تعادل التأثير.
One weekend, one conversation -- hell, one glance --
عطلة نهاية أسبوع، محادثة واحدة... بل لمحة واحدة...
can change everything.
قد تغيّر كلّ شيء.
Cherish those moments of deep connection with other people,
قدِّر لحظات الاتّصال العميقة تلك مع الأشخاص الآخرين،
with the natural world,
مع العالم الطبيعي،
and make them a priority.
واجعلها أولويّة.
Yes, I chase eclipses.
نعم، أطارد الكسوف.
You might chase something else.
وقد تطارد أنت شيئاً آخر.
But it's not about the 174 seconds.
لكن لا يتعلّق الأمر بالـ174 ثانية.
It's about how they change
بل بطريقة تغييرها
the years that come after.
للسنوات التي تعقب ذلك.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)